I flew West. I followed the edge of the desert, trying to find a place to cross. But it was endless.
The golden dunes were laughing at me, teasing me.
“Do you really think you can escape us? Do you really believe no one thought of this before?
Face your fear, little bird. There is no way around us.”
But I couldn’t face it. Not yet. That desert was too big. You couldn’t see the end of it, the sand merged with the sky in the distance, blending in infinity.
“Come on, little bird, called the dunes. The dream is on the other side.”
I flew for days, refusing to give up. There must be a better way.
And then, I reached the ocean. Another barrier.
The Atlantic faced me with all its power, huge waves crashing on the rocks, threatening to blow me to pieces.
In the distance I saw a beach, hedged with coconut trees. I landed in one of them.
After days of helplessly flying over deserted plains, the lush leaves felt like a soft blanket against my body.
I was so exhausted that I fell asleep almost immediately.
I woke up a few hours later to a horrible cacophony.
There were birds perched in all the surrounding trees, hundreds of them, singing and chittering all around me.
After those weeks of lonely travel, I couldn’t face the shock.
“What is this place?” I muttered to myself.
“Welcome to paradise!” Shouted a big red bird, perched on the next branch.
“The tropical haven for gutless birds of all horizons.”
“Why are you saying that?” I asked, defensive.
“Isn’t it why you are here? This is where all migrants who can’t face the big bad desert end up.
Some give up. Some eat to find the courage. Some drink to forget they have none.
Would you like some coconut juice? The sugar will sweep your worries away.”
I ignored him.
“Suit yourself, spoiler”, said the loud bird, and he flew away.
I looked at the crowd. It was a party of birds from across the continent. They were travellers like me, and yet, I felt so alien.
Maybe that red bird was right. Maybe I was just too scared to cross.
Then suddenly I spotted a tiny green dot on a rock by the sea.
It was another willow warbler, staring at the waves in silence.
I approached him. He was probably my age, but there was something different about him.
He looked stronger. His feathers looked longer, sharper. His eyes were more determined.
“So you are also figuring things out, right?”, I said, to break the ice.
“There is nothing to figure out”, he shrugged. “You just need to get ready. I’m flying tomorrow. Clearly, you haven’t started yet.”
“Started what?” I asked
“Moulting. Growing new feathers for the crossing. How else would you expect to do this?”
“But I thought we were only moulting after the journey…” I muttered
“Not us. We are willow warblers. How do you think small birds like us manage to cross the Sahara?
Nature knew she had to give us a hand. Look at my new feathers. Sharp, aren’t they? It’s time to get rid of yours.”
“But how?” I wondered “I’ve had these feathers since I was born.”
“Oh my darling, you’ll have to go through much bigger changes than this. You’re a migrant now. You’ll adapt. It’s our only way to survive.”
So I did. I changed. It took me two weeks. I remember weeping when I saw my first feather fall.
I looked at my reflection in puddles and barely recognised myself.
But alongside my feathers fell the fear. My confidence grew, with every new feather I became stronger.
And then, the day came. And I was ready.